A Guide to the Hartley A. Soule Papers, 1950-1967
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Hartley A. Soule Papers, 1950-1967
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1987-004
2.8 cu. ft. 2 boxes
The collection includes research files, personal notes, film scripts, and publications collected by Soule, an aerospace engineer, on the fields of aviation, aeronautics, and aerospace, particularly on the NACA and NASA programs, including the X-1 and X-15 jets, and the Mercury and Gemini space programs.
Soule, Hartley A., (Hartley Aiken), 1904-1988
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Hartley A. Soule Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1986.
Biographical Information
Hartley A. Soule (1904-1988) was an aeronautical engineer and NASA administrator. He received his B.S. degree from New York University in 1927 and joined the Langley Aeronautical Laboratory of the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA) the same year. His list of positions at Langley included head of the Spin Tunnel Section, Chief of the Stability Research Division, and Assistant Director. Soule assisted in establishing the NASA High Speed Flight Research Center at Edwards Air Force Base and the Mercury Ground Tracking and Data Acquisition System, and led development on the X-1 and X-15 experimental jet programs. He retired from NASA in 1962.
Scope and Content
The Hartley A. Soule Papers include notes, memoranda, calculations, and drawings on the High-Speed Flight Research Station (1950-1954); Research Airplane Program (1953-1957); X-15 program (1958-1962); Dyna Soar program (1957-1962); Projects Mercury and Gemini (1961-1962); and history of the high-speed aircraft program (1963-67). Materials are arranged in two series. Series I: Papers, includes notes, correspondence, memos, subject files, and work projects. Series II: Publications, contains bound reports, scientific publications, and journals.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series. Series I: Papers, is organized by subject/material type. Files are in alphabetical order. Series II: Publications, is organized in chronologically. A list of publications is available in the "Contents List" below.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology; United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Occupations:
Aeronautical engineers.; United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics--Officials and employees.; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration--Officials and employees.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Biographical Information (Box-folder 1-2)
  - High Speed Research Airplane Program (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Memos, Technical Documents (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Mercury Project- Budgets (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Mercury Project- Clippings (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Mercury Project- Correspondence (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Mercury Project- Flight Plans (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Mercury Project- General Reports (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Mercury Project- Photographs (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Mercury Project- Reports From Vendors (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Mercury Project Tracking Systems- Folder 1 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Mercury Project Tracking Systems- Folder 2 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Mercury Project Tracking Systems- Memoranda of Understanding (Box-folder 1-14)
  - NACA Chronological Correspondence (Box-folder 1-15)
  - NACA Clippings (Box-folder 1-16)
  - NACA Photographs (Box-folder 1-17)
  - NACA Sketchings (Box-folder 1-18)
  - NASA Clippings (Box-folder 1-19)
  - NASA Dyna Soar Project (Box-folder 1-20)
  - NASA Flight Research Center (Box-folder 1-21)
  - NASA Manned Space Center Information (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Notes, 1950 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Notes, 1951 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Notes, 1952 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Notes, 1953 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Notes, 1954 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Pacific Missile Range Technical Memoranda- Folder 1 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Pacific Missile Range Technical Memoranda- Folder 2 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Space/Space Flight Publications (Box-folder 1-30)
  - West Africa Publications (Box-folder 1-31)
  - X-1 (Box-folder 1-32)
  - X-15 Clippings (Box-folder 1-33)
  - X-15, John V. Belker Paper on Project Origins (Box-folder 1-34)
  - X-15 Memorandum of Understanding (Box-folder 1-35)
  - X-15 Movie Scripts-Folder 1 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - X-15 Movie Scripts-Folder 2 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - X-15 1965 Program Review Conference (Box-folder 1-39)
  - X-15 Public Relations Materials (Box-folder 1-38)
  - X-15 Public Relations Material(Press Kit) (Box-folder 1-40)
  - X-15 Technical Data (Box-folder 1-41)
- Series II: Publications (Box 2)
  Scope and Content
  Publications
  Project Mercury Progress Report- Contract Number NAS 1-430, 1959
  Project Mercury- A Chronology, 1959
  A Proposal To: NASA- Operation and Maintenance of the Guaymas Sonora Mexico Site, 1960
  Project Mercury Progress Report- Contract Number NAS 1-430, 1961
  National Geographic, September 1961
  Missiles and Rockets, NASA, November 1961
  National Geographic, February 1962
  Results of the First United States Manned Orbital Space Flight, February 1962
  Final Report Project Mercury- Prepared for National Aeronautics and Space Administration, March 1962
  Results of the Second United States Manned Orbital Space Flight, May 1962
  National Geographic, June 1962
  Results of the Third United States Manned Orbital Space Flight, October 1962
  Mercury Project Summary Including Results of the Fourth Manned Orbital Flight, May 1963
  Astronautics and Aeronautics- Charting Apollo Flights/The X-15 Project/Superconducting Coils, February 1964
  National Geographic, 1966
  The Evolution of the Manned Space Flight Network, May 1967
  The Evolution of the Manned Space Flight Network Through Gemini, December 1967
  A Proposal to NASA- Project Mercury Slides, n.d